welcome to a new
wasabi research experience meeting
uh this time um we have a special guest
his name is kailaf he's the creator of
cj dns project basically is a
network that can replace the internet
basically of course is that that is
very ambitious other okay
he will tell us better
and part of this
project is now already supported by
the vip 150 55
in in in bitcoin uh
and bitcoin are other libraries too so
this is an effort that part of the
bitcoin community is doing
in order to have a more diverse
and robust network
collectivity let's say or more resilient
appear to be a
network and where cgi dns
is part of that too
so klev welcome and
we are happy to have you here thank you
very much happy to be here
um yeah so cjdns what is what is cjdns
really
it is a decentralized mesh networking
protocol which is designed to function
under in the context of some of the
notes
uh misbehaving that is some of the nodes
being adversarial
and that's actually very rare in in
routing protocols networking protocols
because
typically if one of the nodes
just starts announcing garbage to the
other nodes
then they will just routing turn the
whole network into a big routing black
hole
um notable exceptions are bgp
and that's obviously how the internet is
routed
but uh bgp is very hard to set up and
so one of the other aspects of cj danis
is it's source routed and that means
that when you send a packet
uh into the network yeah sorry for
interrupt you
i would like to to to go back and
and and ask this question for you what
what is wrong with the
what we have now what do we need yeah
yeah yeah
uh it's all it's all centralized and
it's centralized in the hands of
companies that don't
necessarily like us i mean all you need
to do is go
read the newspaper read the the new york
times or read the um
any one of these newspapers or tv
stations and frankly these are tv
stations that haven't turned an honest
profit in 20 years
and they are being controlled by the
centralized
centralized power structures
and these they are are telling the story
now
that we are the enemy we are the enemy
of the people we are because
we're doing bitcoin mining or any kind
of um
uh encrypted crypto mining that we
are we need to be shut down we need to
be stopped and
the this this saber rattling that we're
seeing
about how it's the biggest uh
environmental disaster in history and
to be clear here this is not the biggest
environmental disaster in history for a
couple reasons
one is because it's actually not that
big
to give you a reference russia flares
off
three times as many as much energy in
gas
just from oil wells that have gas coming
out they just flare it off into this
into the air as the amount of energy
being used by bitcoin so
it's actually not that big it's much
smaller than
other things that have much better
lobbies but the other thing about
crypto mining is that while it does use
a lot of energy
it's also very effective at facilitating
the transition to renewables because
it uses the cheapest energy available
and actually the cheapest
available energy is what comes from
renewables because there's nothing
cheaper than a solar panel once you put
it up
it doesn't cost you anything to just let
that solar panel sit there and run
so i'm very strongly of the belief that
the the the decentralized uh finance and
the crypto
and the mining is actually not uh
cause of uh this massive environmental
degradation
the reason why we're seeing this coming
up in the media is because
these companies these people are lodging
an attack against
the decentralization community and this
is nothing new
we go back to the 90s you have the same
people you know you have bill gates
saying that linux is cancer
and now you know bill gates is buying up
github and there's all of these people
who are moving uh they're making moves
and there is really a war on crypto
going on
so it's very important right now that
we're able to
get our decentralized systems onto their
own network because
if we're going to rely on a network
that's run by the people who are
attacking us
eventually they're going to shut us down
so that's
that's really why cj dns and the pkt
project is so important for me
because the point here is that we're
going to be building
a a mesh based network infrastructure
where
everybody can own a piece of the
internet
i don't i don't want to just model them
here you have a question no no no no
um yes now if you come if you can
tell us what's the the division
right and how the the the
the technology is built
in order to bypass all these
restrictions and
i would like personally know more about
the well i understand the technology but
probably not everybody understands how
it works but
about that and how you
work with your ips as public keys and
all the routings instead of
right what's the address how to route
to that address and how
how everything plays together absolutely
so um cj dns is as i said it is
um uh adversary tolerance so
you know you can have a bad router in
that network and the network's not going
to explode and
there's a couple ways that we do that
one of them is we have
um we derive
the ip address from the public key and
so we're using ip6 addresses and the
address is basically the fingerprint of
the public key
so when we do that we get the um
the ability of you know if so if
somebody says this is my ip address
you know that it's their ip address
because you can just communicate with
them and you
you are able to compare it to their
public encryption key
but that also poses another challenge
which is that
it it um it prevents hierarchical
routing
which is typical of systems uh routing
systems so it's in place of hierarchical
routing
we use a system of source routing and
source routing means that
when you send the packet into the
network it already has the entire path
that needs to take all the way
source to destination and the way that
you
get that route is going to be similar to
the way that you do
what is similar to the way you do a dns
lookup
you're sending a request to a route
server
and that route server is giving you the
path that you should use to get from
point a to point b
and where we're going with this is that
there's going to be
multiple cloud isps what we're calling
them
and these cloud isps operate route
servers and you
just choose which one you want to do
business with and that one
will handle the business of getting your
traffic onto the network and then to
where you want it to be
um why are we doing uh why do we have
this semi-centralized
model of uh cloud isps as opposed to
just doing a fully decentralized let's
route on a dht let's do
everything like that the reason why
we're doing it the way we do it
is because when you have when when your
primary access to the internet is
based on a network you need to be able
to call somebody
when something doesn't work if you're
paying real money to be able to get on
the the network then you need to be able
to make a phone call or whatever
and you need somebody to be able to
handle that situation
and we need that that entity to be there
to be that network operator to be able
to fix that but
we need that not to be a monopoly that
controls everybody's access to
everything
so we have these cloud isps which are a
little bit like
just a vpn company and what they do
is they manage all of the buying and
selling of
bandwidth leases from the people who are
operating the actual infrastructure and
then they find
routes through the the mesh in order to
get you
access to what you need does that make
sense
yes but i think that is something new
isn't it
i mean it was not okay and how how was
that
handled before and how it's not handled
now
yes okay yeah so original cj dns did use
a dht
and um basically we we beat the
we beat the software up as much as we
could and we realized
that there are fundamental limitations
to
a dht based routing model that are
unsolvable
without switching to something that is
different so
basically we can solve a lot of problems
but the problem we can't solve
is my internet doesn't work who do i
call
how do i fix this and because we can't
really solve that who do you call
problem
that's why a fully decentralized routing
infrastructure
just doesn't isn't going to work in the
long term so
in place of that we create an ecosystem
of different entities who can do routing
for you and then you just get to choose
which one you want to work with
okay i see um so
going going down a level
in complexity i mean from a
normal user right because now we are
thinking all the time
normal users and translate this concept
too you know to to my mom
um what does it mean for my mom
what what problem does this technology
solve right right so for an ordinary
person
that's going to be you're going to
install the app
onto your phone on your computer
whatever and then
you're just going to be able to access
the internet fire your neighbor's wi-fi
that's what we're talking about here
you're just getting on onto
your regular internet via your
neighbor's wi-fi
and you buy a vpn and the vpn company
is paying your neighbor to provide you
with that access to the internet that's
what a cloud isp is
it's a vpn which goes and pays
the person who's providing you with the
access to get to that vpn does that make
sense
it makes sense and how successful
is is this right now i mean is it
happening
so we're in really um early stages at
this moment
we have the the packet coin which we're
working on
building all of this infrastructure on
top of
what we need is we need a very very low
cost way to
transact in tokens because when we're
doing
when um we're issuing bandwidth
the bandwidth is going to need to be
tokenized so that people can
buy and sell and trade the right to use
bandwidth on a particular link
and so we need to make a token and it's
not going to work to just use ethereum
because
the gas fees are just unacceptable so
we're working on a project which we call
token strike and
token strike is basically you just make
your own little blockchain
and you sign all the blocks you're the
issuer of the token
you sign all the blocks and all that we
need to do is have a means
by which if the issuer does something
nefarious for example
claw back a token after they sold it to
somebody
then we need to be able to um
i identify that nefarious activity and
have
nodes in the network which can um
which can report to everybody that that
issuer did something bad
and then all of the software will be
configured to not
deal with that issuer until they fix
their stuff
so that's what we're working on in order
to be able to tokenize and issue
bandwidth so
basically we're talking about free
tokens you can just issue you can make a
token you just downloaded the git
repository and you compile it and you
have a token
um and we're gonna need that in order
for
these devices to sell uh
their bandwidth as a token and then
we're gonna need
uh to use lightning network which we're
working on now
in order to transact those tokens using
htlc
contracts now um cjdns and vpn
and vpn app are all in
alpha testing or beta testing you can
you can try out the app on android now
um and the
and what we're what we're using now is
we have uh
um the pkt project is based on
uh a proof proof-of-work algorithm which
is bandwidth hard and the bandwidth
hardness is creating an artificial
demand for bandwidth
um and so unlike a lot of these tokens i
mean i don't need to explain to you guys
necessarily what uh is the difference
between
a token faucet and a proof of work
but i'm finding a lot of people that
don't understand
that a proof of work is proof of fair
issuance
whereas uh all of these other kind of
tokens
these different issuance processes you
can't prove that it was done
fairly so um yeah we we have the only
and this is something else that i
created it's called packet crypt and it
is the only
bandwidth hard proof of work so it's
really just a problem
that is easier to solve if you solve it
together with other miners
and the the packet
blockchain is based on the packet crypt
uh bandwidth hard proof of work so
this is going to incentivize people to
build out
large amounts of bandwidth which we
foresee helping
uh kickstart the the decentralized
bandwidth marketplace
which will finally be used for getting
people off
of the legacy and centralized internet
okay and i don't know if i am the only
one who
would need who had to make questions but
anyway let me go with that so what
you're saying is that basically
my neighbor or i
can become an
internet service provider exactly
exactly
but you're not going to need to do
billing you're not going to need to do
uh customer service you're not even
going to need to do routing
you're just going to set up that device
and it's going to start earning you
packet which i mean you can convert that
to whatever currency you would prefer to
have
okay so i am now an internet service
provider that provides
the the the connection to all my
neighbors
and they pay um
for bandwidth they buy bandwidth to uh
to a company
they they're going to pay a company in a
simple
obvious way you know regular old uh
maybe it's 29
a month whatever whatever that deal is
they're going to pay that to that
company in in that normal
obvious way and then that company is
going to have bandwidth traders
who are going to buy those leases of
bandwidth from you
so that an individual you know grandma
doesn't need to understand
about trading bandwidth and buying the
dip and these kinds of
really complex things that's the job of
financial traders
okay and what is the what is the
um proof of work that is
hard in bandwidth why do we need that
or who need that um the point of
of packet crypt is to create an
artificial demand for bandwidth because
demand drives supply
so when we create a demand for bandwidth
that's going to cause people to do to
roll out more fiber
so think about all of the bitcoin mining
equipment that's just sitting there
collecting dust because it's no longer
profitable right you've got all this
stuff from
five years ago ten years ago and it just
doesn't make any money anymore
with packet crypt if you install a fiber
optic cable
into your area in order to mine packet
crypt that fiber
brings value forever basically so
the work we're leveraging the
externality of pakicrypt
mining in order to get more internet to
more people
okay perfect so basically you know we
are bitcoiners right and we are the
those bitcoiners that many of us
probably don't don't like other
cryptocurrencies
so that's why i'm asking this this thing
so
do you are saying basically that well
the the first design was not
it has some problems and now
with this new um
cloud either sorry i don't remember the
name but
yes this this new um
isp yeah now
of course you need a new token i mean
you need
a way to tokenize the bandwidth in order
to
to create a market to fund with uh
why is that not possible with
i mean you need a market right
right is that market before before
before making my question
is that market already um
running is is is it working
um it's not really off the ground right
yet
but uh that's because we need the token
strike project in order to be able to
tokenize the bandwidth
but okay and let me let me address
because
you asked another you you said another
thing about you know
bitcoin maximalism and i get it like i
i've been there i mean i've been
in the bitcoin community since 2011.
um i know there's a lot of projects that
are pretty shady
and that's that's a reality here so
why should we wh why should we accept
another coin as being legitimate so
i'm going to give you a general answer
which is that
we there is a war on crypto right now
and they are coming after
the uh the work coins first
and then that once they knocked down
once they're able to get
control and stop they're gonna come
after the privacy coins so they're gonna
they're gonna be hitting monero they're
gonna be coming after the work coins
you know they're gonna be coming after
the wasabi wallet the
all of the ways that people can uh
achieve
um liberation from these centralized
powers
they're going to be coming after us and
if we don't work together
then they are going to pick us off one
at a time and you can see in their
newspapers they're already they're
already rattling the sword
so we need to stick together here
because
there is a war against us and it's a war
against decentralization and a war
against open source and a war against
individual liberty
so that's the general answer of why we
can't just
bury our head in the sand and say my
coin is the best everything else is a
scam
and um that uh that's just not going to
work because we will be pried apart and
we will be killed one at a time
and my the the specific answer
why is the packet a thing why don't we
just use bitcoin
etc well packet is a thing for two
reasons and the two reasons are related
to the two differences that it has from
bitcoin
the two fundamental changes that were
made
one of them is that we have uh the
bandwidth hard proof of work
which makes it so that it the the mining
of packet incentivizes the rollout of
network infrastructure the second one is
that
packet has a network steward which is a
basically a founder's fee but the
founder the so-called founder
can be changed via a proof-of-stake
based vote
and that founders fee is used in order
to fund
all these projects in the ecosystem to
develop all the technology
you know bitcoin is it's a great project
but it does not fund the wallets i mean
i'm sure you guys understand
developing wasabi is not easy because
there is no funding for that the funding
is for people who can build
better shot 256 chips
yeah okay rafa
yeah i was just wondering like uh did i
understood correctly that you are using
the
like the same algorithm that bitcoin
uses so
you can make use of these old
like asic devices no uh the algorithm is
very different but the point is that
when you build out infrastructure to
mine packet crypt
that infrastructure includes fiber optic
because you need that bandwidth in order
to mine
so that fiber optic that you've just run
in order to mine packet crypt
when that mining installation becomes no
longer um
profitable that fiber is still there and
that's still bandwidth
that can reach out to people and get
them on the internet
okay got it and you mentioned
that you're using the lightning network
can you elaborate a little bit more like
what part are you doing with that we're
just gonna do our own lightning network
you know i mean
it's uh it's a a bitcoin fork with very
few
actual changes so we're the the point of
this and the fact is
i did not start this project in
2014-1516
because i was waiting for the
transaction scalability that the
lightning network would have
would afford and so then in 2019 2018-19
the lightning network started to reach
maturity and so that was why
i woke up the cjts project cj dennis was
asleep for
uh a good four or five years just
because the other
half of the the necessary technology
just wasn't there yet
okay well something that i have never
never shared before with anyone is that
i am hundred percent sure that
they are going to come
for what's rewarded at least i'm i'm
very
sure so yes i i agree with with you
and i think if if your project
finally uh is
as useful as i think it is
of course i will need to buy those
tokens with
bitcoins because it's it's basically the
currency right
um well one more question and this is my
probably my last question well everybody
most of us probably understand that well
given the
the the ip address is the
the fingerprint of the public key we can
always compute
an encryption key to communicate with
with
the the other end right uh
but after that
i mean i understand it's an end-to-end
encrypted network
what other considerations about privacy
and security but
specifically about privacy and can we
can we learn from your project and
how do you think it can help bitcoin to
to make the bitcoin
the peer-to-peer bitcoin network uh uh
more resilient
well i mean i i think that uh it's not
so much about privacy per se it's about
robustness uh right now
um right now we're just praying that
they don't turn us off
i mean as you said uh that they're
coming for
they're gonna come for a wasabi wallet
and i believe that they're not you know
i have
a strong belief that we're gonna win we
at first they ignored us
and then from say 2014 to 2017 they
laughed at us
you know you remember bitcoin is dead
bitcoin is dead bitcoin is dead all the
newspapers
they just kept saying it and now we're
into the stage that they're fighting us
and we just need to take that fight and
be serious about it because
they are fighting us and they're telling
us they're not fighting us but we're not
going to believe them about that we
can't just
have them say oh yeah there's no war on
crypto just uh
don't believe that you know it is a
propaganda war they're going to try to
to to fight us on on the propaganda
front
and i want to i want to just hammer home
how ridiculous this is yesterday on
twitter um everybody who used the word
memphis in the tweet
was uh banned just and they said oh it
was a bug
oops we made a mistake well guess what
was happening in memphis yesterday
yesterday in memphis tennessee there was
a um
there was a protest against an oil
pipeline and
oil pipelines i cannot uh i cannot
hammer home
enough how uh irresponsible it is
building an oil pipeline right now
because we're just at the precipice
when renewable energy is going to become
so cheap
that um oil is just going to be
uncompetitive
because you don't need anybody greasing
oil jacks to uh
to run a um a solar array you don't need
people shoveling coals around the solar
array
the solar is going to beat the crap out
of all of this stuff
once it reaches the appropriate scale
and
they're still building these oil
pipelines which are just going to
pollute everywhere
and you know these companies are going
to walk away from these oil pipelines
and just say oh yeah it's not our
problem anymore
you know you clean it up and uh they're
still building these things
even now in 2021 so
you know and you have these centralized
platforms
that are creating these bugs in order to
cause people to not be able to talk
about and coordinate a protest against
an oil pipeline
uh yeah no better
yeah i i wanted to say something
but you guys were touching the topic and
then moving
uh away from that and then come back all
the time
i wasn't sure but uh yeah it should be
the right time that
i think you know if if there is
one thing that i i learned from
from wasabi and i think this would be
this because
and and this is a very general point on
on on privacy projects
because at the beginning you know when i
was
telling people that this is what i'm
going to do i'm going to build bitcoin
privacy
and everyone is saying that that no you
can do that because governments hate
privacy
and and only criminals
work on privacy and things like that and
and you know it's it's not
true at all people in government
get how important privacy is it's
just not their first built
and no one is there to remind them that
there are
consequences but you know when when you
reason with people
they they get it i mean sometimes you
just ask them how much
money they have and you know you
instantly make the point because that
question makes them uncomfortable
and oh you you you get privacy
so but but the point is that these
privacy projects are
are always started from these anarchist
libertarian
route and and and i think there is a
very counter productive thing here
is that you know this hacker mindset is
that you have to be super paranoid about
everything that's one uh and and on that
to that is that the libertarian and
anarchist thoughts that
well if you are working on privacy then
you're going to be
thrown down and you know
that's not not happening uh
people get what you're doing what's
what's happening
is when when when someone creates
something and advertises
specifically for goods those are
you know on on the line of
well what should we do with them and
and and those are things those get shut
down but
you know like it's it's not that
often that privacy companies get shut
down
and and in fact the the problem is that
no one dares to even start to work on
privacy because
everyone is saying that it's so
dangerous it's not dangerous
everyone gets privacy privacy is a human
right and and working on it
is is not dangerously natural
um sorry for my round but but
i i think i think we should be more
positive
and yeah but adam
we were i don't know a year ago probably
we were mentioning an internal uh
intelligent agency
that is fighting against who knows what
right and we are in those
reports and in those investigations
again and again so
okay i mean sorry
i think i don't agree with you i don't
i mean i i wanna i wanna jump in here
because
i mean i think this is a really
important topic um
we are clearly in a war
but the war is not with policymakers
policymakers we need to work with them
and we need to explain to them
the importance of decentralizing power
because this power is being centralized
in the hands of a couple of these people
and companies these aristocrats and they
are they're holding this power over
society and they're also holding power
over policy makers
you've got the european union they pass
the gdpr
clearly they care about privacy the and
i mean privacy is considered a
fundamental human right
um and it is not difficult to have this
conversation with policymakers
it's just that a lot of people are
either not doing it because they think
the policy makers are the enemy
which is wrong or they're just
thinking that well take the case of uh
okay cia does uh
does a um a report on wasabi well i mean
ca had a report on
or they had some scraping from uh um
cj dns in their in their internal wiki
that doesn't mean
that they are against us that means that
they want to know
that we're here and we need to have a
public facing
answer to these people we need to have
literature to be able to explain to
policymakers government whatever
what we're about who we're we're
fighting for we're fighting for the
individual
liberty of people and for democracy and
what what what is the other side doing
because the other side doesn't have any
problem putting their lobbyists
into government and then they're using
their lobbyists to try to make
government fight against us so
we need to cut it off where it's
actually happening here
well yes yes i agree with that but
listen
i don't remember if this was nec uh
previous week or a week before that but
the i the european parliament
uh voted for
for for making uh
for i mean the the messaging
server providers and the image provider
have to
to be able to the crypt
basically yeah it's absolutely tragic
what happened
uh last week and um you know this is
this is a loss this is what happens when
we're not in
we're not lobbying you know we're not
talking to policymakers
the other guys go and start talking to
policymakers
and they are going to use the their
relationships with the policymakers to
promote
um to promote policy which uh
helps them to continue and establish
their monopolies over control of the
the individual people so you know we win
some we lose some
the policymakers are not our enemy um
they
are being pulled by our real enemy
okay anyway they are the one that vote
for these
things for just for for those that don't
understand what
what this means is for example uh it is
not possible to have end-to-end
encryption anymore because
if i provide this the chat service and i
i need to be able to decrypt your
messages
that means that end-to-end encryption is
not possible anymore i mean
you the the communication can be
encrypted
um but
no end-to-end let's say i don't
please go ahead yeah hi
so i was just wondering because this
sounds a little bit like the tour
project but the
and you have a similar concept on
providing bandwidth and
even though door itself doesn't really
do any accounting on the bandwidth but
you actually have a privacy layer on top
of it
so i was wondering if there is a similar
risk model
related to your project as being a host
host of the service as running a tour
exit node
what do you think uh it's a bit similar
it's it's a bit similar
as far as your risk profile when you're
running a vpn
um but unlike tor
we're not trying to have anonymity of
the um of the person versus the the exit
so we're not trying to be a strong
anonymity
our point is to have a strong network
that is
um robust and resilient to people
shutting it down
centralized power um tor is going in a
slightly different direction where
they're
they're really trying to make it so that
nobody knows who anybody
is and that's a very hard problem to
solve and it's a very specific problem
so tor and cj dns and packet will
always tend to coexist because
they exist on different planes and for
different purposes
if it's okay another question
yes please yeah uh i was just wondering
it's a little bit difficult to get a
layer layer 2 vpn set setup
at least i don't know any service
providers who would actually do that
do you support layer two um
no we are layer two we are a layer two
um because we're not we're not actually
doing ethernet
um ethernet in my opinion it's not
really that useful
it's it's because ip
doesn't scale down and ethernet doesn't
scale
up we ended up with these two layers
cj dns scales both directions so
um on top of cj dns we just put an ip
packet because it's compatible with
with ordinary software i mean you could
do
ethernet over cjdns just like why that's
kind of the point
regions yeah i mean you could do it it's
just like it's just like doing ethernet
over
like uh packet over sonnet or sdh it's
it's
really the similar concept you just have
to write a little bit of code to
connect it together cj dance is a
transport it'll transport anything you
want
okay good to know thanks
yes short for coin join dns
no um it's it's uh
because my initials are cjd and um
there's a long story about that yeah
originally it was supposed to be a dns
system
but um we pivoted it into uh
being a routing system because uh
routing is actually easier to solve than
dns dns is a
deep political problem that is
not my favorite problem to try to solve
okay do you know about um
the lucky project the project that it
comes from the
monero community
it is not it is not similar but it's a
networking
solution similar to tor and they have a
coin to
i mean a token i don't know if it is for
bandwidth i mean it has to be for
bandwidth because
what what else right do you know
something about that
in order to make a comparison or to
do you have seen to yeah i i know
i i spoke with the developers of loki um
yeah it's a it's a monero fork as i
recall
um i mean here's the thing they're
working on anonymity
and they they want to do an anonymity
network um
the fundamental thing is that we want to
do is
we want to do infrastructure we want to
get people access to other people
without having to go through networks
that can be turned off
that's that's like the key fundamental
aspect of packet
whereas um anonymity is just like
we can solve anonymity later once we
control
infrastructure and people that uh the uh
the bill gates is
of the world are not going to turn this
off on us
yeah it's a good answer okay thank you
i want to ask the same question so that
the main difference is between
cj dns and nimtek i don't know if
you know it but it's similar
is that nim mix now yeah yes
um i've just just vaguely heard about it
but i mean if
the point is anonymity then it's
it's really the same answer it's it's
really like
we are going to be light on anonymity
because anonymity costs you it's it's
effort you have to do software
development you have to waste resources
because you're doing onion routing
that's
more resources more latency that is
a worse quality of service for people
our primary objective is to find a way
to get people their their primary
internet access
that they don't have to that works 100
that they can go stream the videos they
want to stream whatever they want to do
and then we can layer the anonymity on
top of that
and that's a primary internet access
that's not going to get shut down
because it's decentralized
by the way we have all um a
meeting um specially for
mixnets so
it is already available in youtube if
someone wants to
to know more about uh
mixed just a question
imagine i want to be an internet service
provider right
how can i buy i mean because someone has
to provide
the service to me and what is the
legal i mean i'm sure it's different
from country to country but how can i
i buy that it is possible it is easy
does the telecommunication companies
have a problem with that
can you tell us a bit absolutely so
um when you're buying internet in a data
center
it is actually very easy to do there are
lots of providers there are lots of
companies
um it's very competitive and so
in the data centers the internet is not
there we don't have a problem of people
like potentially turning things off
that's not really where the problem lies
and it's also cheap it's competitive
it's cheap there's lots of options
the problem is between the data center
and your house
because that's where you've got one or
two companies
they have not upgraded their networks in
20 years
they are only they only move when
there's somebody threatening them
and basically the way that they move is
to try to crush that threat so that they
they don't have to move anymore you
remember back in the 90s we had lots of
dial up
there was a big explosion of different
internet service providers
and then all of a sudden the cable and
telephone companies they created dsl
and cable and then they they just
squeezed all of those little companies
out of existence and then
we've been living most of us have been
living with dsl and cable ever since
so if there's no competition in the in
the market
then these companies will do absolutely
nothing
so how would you get a
fast internet connection so um you can
you can contract if you let's say you're
in a you're an area where there's no
fiber
you can contract to get fiber run to
your house and
there are companies that will do this
for you it's very expensive
but if you're making gonna make money
off of the people
in your town then this is potentially
worthwhile for you
and the the way you do it you find one
of these companies you contract with
them
the company that owns the telephone
poles is usually
legally required to allow somebody to
put
their their cables on them as long as
they follow
certain rules that's why you have the
phone the cable and the uh
the electricity running on the same
telephone poles the
if the electric company owns the polls
they're required to let the phone
company use them if the phone company
owns the polls they're required to let
the electric company use them
so based on this legal requirement
you're able to use
a company that will run fiber right to
your house
you're going to pay for it but it will
get you internet
to the nearest data center and then from
there you're able to
um you're able to release those lines
and then you're able to get
a um you're able to get fast internet
which you can then sell to your
neighbors
excellent thank you guys someone do
someone has a question
for kayla
okay then what next okay
maybe i just i just like to repeat what
you
what maybe might take away from
from what the g dns is
is that i i imagine this is something
that
goes lower than than the
anonymity networks like thor and the new
project
today or i2p but it is going to a lower
player a little bit and it is only
trying to tackle
um would you say scienceship resistance
is is this what it provides and and then
we would have a standard resistance
internet
and on top of that it would be actually
well probably anonymity networks would
work
better and support that too is that the
first memory or
or am i yeah yeah yeah yeah
totally it's a it's about censorship
resistance
and censorship takes many forms
you don't think about your you're being
censored because they haven't upgraded
your the quality of your internet in 20
years
but that is actually a form of
censorship you don't have fast internet
that is a way that you are being
prevented from
communicating
all right oh wait so so wait
yes this this can be let's say
layer one and also layer two i mean it
it works
also it can work also as um
how to say um i
i i forget the word but basically
um it can work on top of the existing
infrastructure too
am i right yeah yeah yeah it works it
works either
on you can anything that could connects
two computers together
including the existing internet is
working for
transporting data for cg dns
excellent thank you i wanted to make one
final like uh um plug here
is that um because the packet system
ecosystem has this institution of the
network steward
we are always looking for uh projects
and people
who are developing technology in the
space who need that funding and that
because um the the packet
network steward funds whatever will help
benefit the objective of the project so
um it's something that wasabi wallet can
potentially participate in
or any of the the side projects of
wasabi wallet
can potentially participate by proposing
a project to the the packet network
steward
and that can be funded it'll be funded
in packet but you know you can liquidate
that to whatever you want
and that's a way that we're able to
bootstrap
a lot of the technology that we need for
this network to work
and that that again is one of the
reasons why we couldn't have just done
this
on top of bitcoin because we need that
aspect of the financing to build out all
of this infrastructure
that we need
yes sorry one more question in order to
have an idea of the
magnitude of the growing of this product
do you have any idea how many let's say
clients
uh are running this
this software oh it's uh it's a it's a
good question
i mean i can tell you a couple numbers i
mean there's about 200 people
in our um chat which is um
packet.pkt.chat
so you know you can go there and hang
out with cool people there's about 200
people in the chat there
um there's about 300 people on telegram
um i don't know exactly how many wallets
there are how many nodes and so on
um these are you know just kind of
nebulous numbers
um i that's that's basically what i know
and then what is that e probably a
project or
or website or community what is that
well uh hyperborea was a
i mean i i say was it's technically it
still exists but
really it was about research on the
cjdns project and that
and building the researching the the
technology of cjdns
that was going on between 2012 and
2014-15 or so
for the most part hyperborea is not
really
active anymore a lot of the people who
wanted to do
websites that were kind of in their own
little network
um have moved over to the egg drizzle
project
and so research continues with igdrissel
which by the way
are great friends of the packet project
um
but the uh yeah the hyperborea
as it were is not really a thing anymore
and we're moving cj dns from the
research
phase to the industrialization phase
through
the packet project
okay thank you i have one more question
i i
i always have more questions well
you know here sometimes giving we are
touches we
discuss what is the best programming
language
useless a useless discussion but now
if i understand this correctly you are
let's say
writing more new versions
in rust is that correct yeah
yeah i mean why why because i
previously used c and i find it just
unconscionable at this point to continue
developing
c or c plus plus because
they're they're bugs and those bugs are
going to harm people
and it's just like you you
you memory corruption it's never done
and like the person
the very people who say oh i'll never
have memory corruption bugs i'm too good
i'm a good programmer that's only for
idiots
those are the ones who create the real
problems those are the ones who
create problems that in the end lots of
people get harmed by that
so i mean i get it you know you've got a
legacy project
it's in cc plus plus you you just live
with that that's how it is you do your
best you
you use c comp you use whatever you can
no exact stack that that kind of stuff
which by the way
um my one patch to bitcoin was to turn
on no exec stack in bitcoin so that um
you know certain really simple 1990s era
stack smashing attacks wouldn't work um
but you know at this point we want to be
doing things securely
the way that you're gonna you gotta do
things we can't just keep sticking with
uh
uh 20 30 40 years old languages
that's my opinion anyway
yes we have some similar discussions i
remember here
one more question about that how do you
how do you see the productivity of
your the people programming in rust
in comparison with with previous
experience
programming in c or c plus plus because
personally i i i'm not a rush programmer
i
tried to to learn it many many years ago
and i was
fighting against the compiler everything
that i did was
wrong basically so i said okay i i will
try this a couple of years
right after okay well rust has just
very recently become onto my radar as
something that's
there i mean uh you know five years ago
it just wasn't there yet you know it was
still in research phase
so now rust in my opinion it's there
so you can just use it um
and as far as productivity yeah i mean
you pay a little bit of productivity in
terms of
when you're writing the code it's a
little bit less productive than if
you're
if you're a c plus plus person you know
you can just bang out the c
plus plus but where i get major
productivity improvements is when i'm
reviewing the code
because if i've got somebody who's
making a contribution to cjdns and
they're like oh yeah i've got a big huge
piece of code here
i have to read that line by line to say
well is that
is that a memory corruption issue is
that a memory corruption issue is that a
memory corruption issue
and i know i'm not going to be perfect
you know i'm going to slip by
i can't say honestly that nothing's
going to slip by
you know we're only human here and
when somebody makes a contribution in
rust i can just look at that i can go
through it much
more quickly you know does have any
unsafe i can
i'm just not having to be as paranoid
when i'm doing code review and i'm sure
you understand the same thing you know
you get if you especially if you accept
anonymous pull requests into the wasabi
wallet
you got to look at that code and you're
like well
is that somebody trying to do
underhanded crap to try to fool me you
know and that's just
like that's the worst thing ever
yeah yeah well we have now the the
problem with the
with memory because we're programming in
a managed
language and we have a guy that's a
garbage collector
uh what do you add but anyway reviewing
reviewing code carefully because we
are we we have i mean
people move a lot of money with
uh bitcoin wallet and
a mistake is could be very
very very expensive in terms of
reputation and well
there's a company behind so probably it
could
be more than reputation so yes reviewing
is
is a problem i cannot imagine if i have
to keep track of
a collection of pointers
yeah it could be really hard yeah